Guide to the Museum Studies Department records, 1976-2002 RG0092
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Museum Studies Department records
1976-2002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0092
2.75 Linear Feet 2 record center boxes 1 document box 1 slim document box
Collection includes departmental history, sample exams, reports, course proposals, meeting minutes, syllabi.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from Museum Studies Department.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Museum Studies department of The George Washington University, was founded in 1976 by a committee of University professors consisting of Dr. Humphery from Anthropology, Dr. MacDonald from Art History, and Dr. Mergen from American Studies. The University was one of the first graduate schools to establish a museum studies based program.
In the early 1980s Marie Malaro, a legal advisor to the Smithsonian Institution, took over as director of the program. Under her direction, the course selection increased as did the number of students enrolled in the program. Malaro retired in 1997 and was succeeded by Ildiko DeAngelis, who also previously served as a legal advisor to the Smithsonian Institution for over 10 years.
The department was created to provide students with a broad background in museum studies knowledge, including a variety of specialized approaches to a museum careers, with concentrations in such areas as conservation, collections management, and exhibiting techniques. Due to the large variety of museums in the District of Columbia, the University offers a unique resource for interested students. Not only are classes taught by professionals who work in local museums, including the Smithsonian, many of these classes are taught within the museums themselves.
The Museum Studies department offers a 2 year Master's program or a one year certificate program. The department offers three concentrations within the museum field: collections management, exhibit design, and administration. Furthermore, the program requires an academic core in a specialized field which includes, but is not limited to art, anthropology, history, or American studies.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include departmental history, sample exams, reports, course proposals, conferences, meeting minutes, syllabi, National Park Service Workshops, and Taiwan Project. They range in dates from 1976 to 2002, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Department of Museum Studies. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized in three series of departmental records.
Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Museums -- Collection management; Museums; Museum administration; Exhibit design; Washington (D.C.); George Washington University; George Washington University. Museum Studies Department
- Departmental records, 1978-1986; RG0092 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains departmental history, sample exams, reports, course proposals. They range in date from 1978-86.
  - History of Museum Studies Program, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Past Course Descriptions, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - MSTD Annual Reports, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, Director, M. Shapiro, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - MSTD Committee Material, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - MSTD Activities: Lectures and Events, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brochures and Description of Program, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - MSTD Newsletters: Past Issues, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - MSTD Sample Exams, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - MSTD Statistics, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Course Proposals: Zoo Biology, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11.1)
    General note
    In box labeled 11-A
  - Course Proposals: Museum Evalution, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11.2)
    In box labeled 11-B
  - Course Proposals: Museum Exhibit Fabrication, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11.3)
    In box labeled 11-C
  - Course Proposals: Museum History, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11.4)
    In box labeled 11-D
  - Course Proposals: Conservation Microscopy, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11.5)
    In box labeled 11-E
  - Course Proposals: Exhibition and Evalution, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11.6)
    In box labeled 11-F
  - Course Proposals: Collections Management, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11.7)
    In box labeled 11-G
  - Course Proposals: Intro. to Museum Studies, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11.8)
    In box labeled 11-H
  - Course Proposals: Inorganic Materials, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11.9)
    In box labeled 11-I
  - Course Proposals: Museum Accessibility/Handicapped, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11.1)
    In box labeled 11-J
  - Course Proposals: Problems in Museum Interpretation, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11.11)
    In box labeled 11-K
  - Course Proposals: Organic Materials, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11.12)
    In box labeled 11-L
  - Course Proposals: Non-profit Accounting, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11.13)
    In box labeled 11-M
  - Course Proposals: Publications, K. Taylor, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11.14)
    In box labeled 11-N
  - Course Proposals: Museum Registration, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11.15)
    In box labeled 11-O
  - Course Proposals: Current Development, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11.16)
    In box labeled 11-P
  - Course Proposals: Collections Management, MCM, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11.17)
    In box labeled 11-Q
  - Course Proposals: Collections Management, Spiess, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11.18)
    In box labeled 11-R
  - Course Proposals: Collections Management, K. Taylor, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11.19)
    In box labeled 11-T
  - Course Proposals: Intro. MSTD 202, Shapiro, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11.2)
    In box labeled 11-U
- Departmental records, 1978-1986; RG0092 Series 2; .5 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  Acquisition note
  On June 8, 2015 the publication 2005 Marie Malaro Excellence in Research & Writing Award The Museum Studies Program The George Washington University was added to box 2 of this unprocessed series. It came to Special Collections in May 2015 from David Killian, Collection Development Librarian for Museum Studies. Thus it was not part of the original donation and was not part of box 2 when originally donated. But was added to this unprocessed series as a way to keep it with the collection for when this series is processed.
  This series contains departmental history, sample exams, reports, course proposals. They range in date from 1978-86. Also included in this series (box 2) is the publication 2005 Marie Malaro Excellence in Research & Writing Award The Museum Studies Program The George Washington University
- Departmental records, 1981-1983; RG0092 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains newsletters that range in date from 1981 to 1983. They contain information about the Museum Studies Department.
  - Museum Studies, Program of--Publications, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)